the last part I want to discuss is about some
challenges
and issues when it comes to threading
the plan here is to show you to give you more
evidence
about what
I said since the very first lecture
that is when you want to do something fancy
more advanced that
gives you better performance you need to pay
a cost and
it gets more complicated
so I'm going to give you some hints about
why
it's more complicated
and aspects that who designs a system that
supports multi-threaded
processes needs to think about
let's start with the semantics of fork or
exec
so this is the code
we discussed already in a previous video
so we have the process calling
fork two processes
they copies we check if the fork was successful
and if that
is the case we have the child process running
exec to replace the memory and run a different
program
and the parent process that is waiting for
the child
and waiting that everything is done and finally
exiting
you can think about questions like this does
fork duplicate
only the calling thread or all the threads
answer
it depends
I'm not saying this because you need to know
what is actually
being done inside the fork
it depends on the implementation you have
of it and the
Unix system you're using
but the point I'm trying to make is that such
a question
arises now because we have multi-threaded
processes
if each process had a single thread we would
not need to
think about this kind of things
similar questions can be made for the
exec although
in practice exec will replace everything as
it is to replace everything
with a different program
it will start with one thread usually would
be really strange
to keep all the threads since what the next
program
will do is potentially
completely different from what the current
one is doing
another aspect to take it account is that
of handling signals
so signals are used in Unix systems
to send messages
between threads and processes
when a process runs wait it asks the
operating system
to notify it when
for example the child process has terminated
all these messages
are handled by the kernel through signals
now if you have single-threaded processes
and you send a
signal to a process it's pretty easy who you
should contact
you in this case is the operating system
it's easy to understand who the kernel should
contact the process
which is the single-threaded process
on the other
hand if a process has multiple threads then
you can imagine
that you can have legit questions like this
should I deliver
the signal to a specific thread in the process
and if the answer is yes
how do I know which is the specific
thread that should get the signal
or should I notify all the threads
of the process
which one of the two is the
option to go might depend
on the process you are running
both options might be valid
and you might want as an operating system
to provide
functionalities so that you can choose which
one
of the two
what I am trying to say here simply put
is that all the handling of signals
becomes way more complicated
once you start having multi-threaded processes
instead of single-threaded ones
you also need to take into account
how you hand the cancellation of
threads
there are two ways in which you
can go and you have the details here
actually in the next slide you also have
more details in the table about
how it actually works
simply put you can either terminate
the target thread immediately
so if thread A
says kill thread B then this will be done
but
what
you
usually do is that you actually signal your
intention so if A wants to terminate B, A signals
the intention
of doing this to B
but it asks B to actually terminate itself
as soon as possible
and this is called deferred cancellation
the idea here is that you want B to stop
but you can
wait a bit until it's done completing whatever
it is doing
so if B is operating on some file and
you want to stop B
if you kill it immediately then it might die
without storing
the file to disk for example
and as we will discuss later on since there
might be buffering
in the main memory terminating the program
before it's done
in an abrupt way might create problems
so you do this differed
cancellation and you say I would like you
to stop
and the target thread in this case will periodically
check whether
it got a signal that it should stop and in that
case close
whatever it is doing
and the terminate
and you have this function here pthread_testcancel
for this